The doctor told me this is colon cancer.
>> This is David Rumpka. He was an
engineering director at both Netflix and
Facebook. And now that he's retired, he
was completely [music] unfiltered.
>> And I know this is going to be
controversial. I I personally don't love
lead code. They nail these interviews
and they get in and their engineering
work is terrible.
>> As a hiring director, he had some
genuine stories that really stuck with
me.
>> He's like, "Aren't you going to try to
talk me out of it?" I was like, "Yes,
you're my friend. as your boss, I don't
want to lose you, but as your friend,
I'm like, how can you say [music] no?
>> Early in his career, he had an
experience that changed his perspective
forever.
>> So, while I was in the hospital
reflecting, I realized that like this is
wrong.
>> Here's the story of his [music] 36-year
career.
So, about Netflix, how did it differ
from the other companies you had worked
at?
every company I worked at before
Netflix. Well, I can't really talk much
about Hughes aircraft, GM Hughes, but
starting with like the IBM and moving
through even these smaller companies. If
we had these primadas, right, they have
may be really smart, but they can be
really difficult to work with. People,
they yell at you, they whatever. And the
company's value they would actually
build I mean I worked at the company in
the '9s
this apparently the most critical
engineer oh if we lose him we're toast
the guy's cubicle was so full of junk
the walls were bulging out [laughter]
he was like a packrat and he wouldn't
engage with anybody and he would work
all night and fix problems. He was
always the hero. And the managers, they
did had no understanding what he did or
whatever, but all they know is if he
quits, we're in trouble. Well, he quit,
right? And guess what? The company
didn't die, right? Once he was out of
the way, he went to do something else.
Everybody else moved in. They actually
had other people understand just nobody
could work with this guy. And he
established himself as the center of
gravity for this one big area of our
system. I think it was the storage. I
can't remember this the part of it, you
know. And I had this kind of same thing
at innerv video. I had some some
colleagues. I had some really really
good colleagues that that actually
helped form my technical they gave me my
technical education. But there were some
people that are really really hard to
work with and scream at you and yell at
you and they would be wrong and they can
never admit it you know and you know the
customers you know customers have a
problem. We try to tell them like their
code is wrong and they just they respond
with screaming and yelling at you. And I
got to Netflix and it's like we don't
have anybody like that, you know? And it
was written in the culture deck. They
don't hire brilliant jerks, right? If
you're a person who's always going off
the rails, who's yelling and screaming,
who's difficult to work with, who makes
yourself unapproachable, they're going
to let you go. And they don't care how
smart you are or how what level of
contribution because they realize and
they you know this this was
revolutionary in 2000 in the early
2000s. You know somebody who grows up in
meta yeah your point is I mean because
that's way modern you know the the fang
companies at least the ones I know
Google Netflix Meta that's the way they
work now but that wasn't like that. So
it was I was like wow that was the first
thing and then the second thing during
my interview Patty McCord who was a
chief people officer who inter at that
time as a very small company interviewed
everybody and had to bless every hire
and you think about that and and and I
learned I will say I learned more from
Batty I think even than Reed as far as
being a good leader and being a really
like a good collaborative teammate. Um
but during our interview she said
something that just floored me. She says
um we don't value 247 work here and if
you just come in and work all the time
we're not going to be impressed. And it
was like if you want to impress us blow
us away with what you can do in an 8
hour day. And I also you know and she's
like but also let us you know like we
like people that like if they're laying
in bed at night and they can't sleep
odds are they're thinking about one of
their problems at Netflix that they're
trying to fix. these are the people we
want. And I'm just like, wow. And and so
I got into Netflix and and I will say
that was absolutely true that
I did see people fall into that 24/7
trap and and you know when people work
like that, one you feel it's a
compulsive need, you know, cuz you're
you know, you don't have a team to
support you. You're doing everything
like if I stop everything the company's
going to fail. And two, but then you
hate it because you're, you know, and
and I just remember there was a meeting
and he was like, I'm just working all
the time. I can't work like this
anymore. And Patty was in the meeting
and she says, "Hey, first I want to
thank you for everything you've done to
try to help us be successful and not
fail and that you're even willing to
work 24/7." Now, the second thing I have
to say is don't do this again.
You need to figure out, you're a
manager, you're a leader, you need to
figure out how to set your team up so
that you don't have to work all the
time. And if you want to be successful
here, you have to do that. That's just
that was unthinkable in 2008, 2009. Um
and I even had a you know similar
situation later at Netflix because you
know we were still working on the you
know the a lot of you know continuous
build deployment these things didn't
exist right things everybody takes for
granted they didn't really they were
just coming out you know Google other
companies were just getting these in
place and we had some serious stability
issues when we tried to go to continuous
deployment and and I was over talking to
it and he was a phenomenal engineer I
still engag engage with a guy. We both
uh retired, but but I was over talking.
I said to him by the weekend, he goes,
"Well, it must be nice having weekends
off." I said, "What do you mean?" He
said, "We have if we quit, if we stop
working, you know, these systems go
down. We can't keep them running." And
and he was, you know, the other people
that he worked with all kind of came out
and I feel like I'm going to, you know,
I got to get out of here, right? But I
left and I set up a one-on-one with him
the following week and I got in a room
with him and I said, "You need to take a
vacation." He's like, "I can't." you
know, we if we don't if we're just
keeping this rob and I told him straight
up, I said, "If this company cannot
survive without you here on the clock,
we got a problem. You need to take a
vacation. And I don't care what happens.
If things break, they break. Take your
vacation." And um and he did. He went
and took a week off and he came back
and, you know,
refreshed. he had been with his family
and you know and and and
the other people on that team took time
off and they were able actually rather
quickly to stabilize the system because
they quit trying to do what the manager
was telling them they needed to do. They
decided this is how we're going to
stabilize it. And then all of a sudden
this team that was killing themselves
just by forcing themselves to take time
off was a actually able to come back
refreshed, think about the problem, not
think about how to keep the systems
running. and they were actually able to
have that time off. So that was part of
net that I mean that was fundamental
piece of Netflix culture. Patty told me
we all have lives. See I I don't want to
work all weekend. I want to go home. I
want to enjoy my life, you know, and so
I really did appreciate that. Um
and I will say also
Netflix was built with strong and
visionary leaders. Reed Hastings had a
vision from early 90 or from late 90s.
And he said if if I wanted to do like
DVDs by mail, this would be called DVDs
bymail.com.
It's called Netflix because DVD by mail
for him was a stepping stone to what he
believed was the future was streaming
video. And he didn't know how it was
going to happen. He Reed's not a video
expert, but he built a team out of
really good leaders and a really good
small team of really good engineers and
it's like we're going to solve this
problem.
>> How did uh Netflix culture change as a
company grew?
>> You know, obviously the the the Netflix
culture memo with think is something of
legends, right? People talk about it and
what I would have to say about there's a
few things I would say about that. First
of all, for me personally,
[clears throat] because people would ask
others, is this how it is at Netflix?
And they would say, yeah. They would ask
me, I say, no, it's what we aspire to
be. The culture memo is aspirational.
>> What is the culture memo?
>> Oh, it's like it's like the original it
was like some slides, like 15 slides
talking about we don't hire brilliant
jerks. We want really smart people. We
want to inspire people to sail the seas.
We don't want to tell them how to build
a ship, right? We we you know we um you
know we we pay top of market. We uh we
uh you know we have a keepers test which
you know basically we're aggressive at
firing people. We're not afraid to make
mistakes. Those were kind of all baked
into the culture memo. But it was you
know putting that out when it was put
out you know in like 20078 the original
culture. It was that stack was actually
pretty revolutionary at the time. A lot
of that, you know, freedom of
responsibility, the whole the ability of
hiring really good people and not
staying out of their way, giving them
the context of what needs to be done,
helping them understand why it matters
and then expecting them to go and
execute on that without you
micromanaging them, you know, trust
basically trust, freedom,
responsibility, trust and you know, and
[clears throat] so uh these were all
really really key parts of the Netflix
culture and I think as a small
it if what enabled Netflix to be
successful where others other companies
didn't was that culture built around
exceptional talent what not just
engineers everybody I worked with at
Netflix was exceptional right um the
marketing people the the the content
people product every HR I mean and they
were all learning I was learning from
everybody right I learned how to build a
good team through my HR partners they
weren't just you giving me resumes and
and scheduling interviews, right? They
were challenging me on my higher no hire
decisions. They were, you know, pushing,
you know. So, I think that was
fundamental. [clears throat] I I did
notice as the company was growing that
that that culture was not scaling well.
And I I'll give you a good example. One
thing Netflix didn't wasn't really big
on was individual achievement.
Everything was one as a team. Everything
we did was a team. Nobody ever said,
[clears throat] for example, when we
shipped the PS3, that revolutionary
rule breaker, you know, we did something
so crazy, Sony, the DVD division at Sony
saw what we were doing and said, "Please
stop. We didn't design the PS3 to do
this. Please stop." But we didn't stop.
We broke the rule. We we delivered a
system. In the end, they didn't say,
"Hey, Scott Woo and David were the, you
know, and Mitch were the were the
foundational engineers that made this
all possible." It was Netflix one, you
know, and at the time that was really
good. But as things got bigger, this all
gets lost, right? And um and I feel like
as the company got bigger and instead of
doing one or two things, you're starting
to do many things. individual
contributions which are still huge. I
mean engineering that's the way
engineering works. We're starting to get
lost, right? And if you don't credit
individuals for great engineering work,
who gets the credit?
So leaders and and I realized that that
was something I struggled with you. We
didn't have levels. All engineers were
equal. There was only an engineer, a
senior software engineer period. You
could make your title anything you
wanted. You could call yourself the, you
know, software engineering video guru.
You could call yourself, you know,
whatever. You couldn't put manager,
director,
VP, or chief in your title if you
weren't one of those. But other than
that, your business card could say
anything you wanted. Um, but there was
only one software engineering level. And
as a small company with just senior
people has worked. But as we started
hiring more juniors, uh when you as
teams grow, you're going to have really
strong engineers, you're going to have
good engineers, and then you're going to
have weak engineers. And if you don't
have a system in place that can
understand that and and and recognize
and and objectively determine who's who,
then it you start having challenges with
your best people. it ultimately not
having a good objective process for
recognizing wins, achievements and
rewarding those wins and achievements
ultimately impacts your best people who
end up leaving. So that was something I
was struggling with. I I had was trying
to argue they do have levels now at the
time like by the late teens I was
arguing like we really need levels
because we have really senior engineers
and we've got juniors. We have people
who understand our system from one end
and the other and can do incredible work
and we have other they're good engineers
but they're just learning and and so um
I think these were some of the aspects
that didn't scale. Um other things like
I mentioned in the early days Patty
McCord who's one of the great
influencers in my life interviewed
almost every single hire that come in
the company. Obviously you can't keep
doing that. Reed Hastings have like
these really small one-on ones with new
like four new hires at a time. he would
sit and give you like an hour of his
time to ask questions to talk of share
about you you who you were and and what
excited you about Netflix.
[clears throat]
Obviously he couldn't do that. So
eventually Reed would show up with a
couple other leaders with 100 people in
the room or whatever you know and
eventually I think they probably
couldn't even do that. So these are
these are all challenges to scale where
you know but
you know
success right success means that you
know you success means a small company
becomes a big company if that's how you
measure success and success at Netflix
was measured in you know building this
product that's going to reach the world.
So success means you're going to be big
and it means that things that were easy
or worked well at a small company don't
necessarily grow with you. So you you
have to make those adjustments. I
haven't been there for six years. I'm
sure I know they brought levels and I'm
sure they've done a lot of work to
change that. But when I left it, I felt
the culture was struggling with a
culture memo that was perfect for a very
small aggressive engineering focused
company.
>> If everyone is the same level, how did
they compensate people differently or or
you know, imagine someone who's a new
grad that joins Netflix compared to
industry veteran video expert,
>> right? Well, I mean, at the time,
Netflix generally didn't hire new grads.
I will say generally because I found
lots of clever ways to break rules and
and work around um you know, around
that. But generally speaking, and and
they had this concept of personal top of
market, right? So, if I work and they
also had this interesting thing in their
culture memo that they encouraged people
to interview often.
So, if I got a job, I'll just put it out
there. My starting salary when I joined
Netflix, which at the time was a good
starting salary, was 175K a year.
Somebody may think, wow, you know,
you're 15 years in, that's all you got.
But, I mean, you know, but at the time,
2007, that was a really solid starting
salary.
If a year later,
I would have interviewed Google and they
would have offered me 200,000, I would
have gone and told my manager, hey, I
got this offer for 200,000. a manager
would have said had a major choice. Go
work at Google or we're going to give
you pay raise, right? Because your top
of market, your personal top of market
has now moved and somebody else who came
in at 175 may never may not move that
way. But also over time, you
[clears throat] know, um the the and
this this was incumbent on us as
leaders, which I took very serious and
and the managers that that worked with
me is understanding where the market is,
understanding where offers are, who's
getting offer, how much is Google
paying, right? Meta, you know, Meta was
late to the video game, but by 20, it
was Facebook at the time. By 2015,
Netflix was very aggressive. I'm sorry,
Meta was very aggressive building a
video team. How much were they offering
our people? who was interviewing with
with you know if somebody you know we
understood their skill level went and
got an interview from one of these other
companies got an offer that was twice
what we were paying everybody that means
we have to adjust our compensation twice
right that's the way it worked but again
in the early days it worked well but as
you get more and more people that
becomes muddied and it becomes muddied
in several ways one way is that and it's
unsustainable um Let's say an engineer
who was one of your great engineers did
get this offer at 2x our comp and we
reviewed it at a senior leader level and
said yeah we really need this person and
this is our market let's pay them
three years later this engineer is
making more than almost everybody else
still contributing at that level but
because there's no performance review
there's no there's no a leader could
look and say why is this person making
three times this person because all they
see is numbers they have no context and
that's where the system started breaking
and and then we would have like, you
know, hey, you know,
I I'll just say this. We had a some
engineers some that we interviewed and
offered jobs at X and they all got
competing offers at Facebook or like
five of them at 1.2x
and we're in a room and I said, well,
the culture member says we adjust our
offer to 1.2. Well, you know, it was
they didn't understand. We didn't have
baked into our system didn't have
understanding of how compensation worked
like that. We didn't have a concept of
leveling and so all of a sudden nobody
could rationalize that 1.2x. Now they
have the leveling and I think that they
would very oh you got an offer an IC6 at
at at Google. Okay, we understand and by
the way we can all go out to you know
levels.fyi and see what that range is
and okay we can adjust you.
But we didn't have that back then. So
that's where things got really
challenging and and and and as a leader
who who you know I valued like building
the team and and keeping a good team and
paying them,
>> you know, market, right? I didn't want
to overpay anybody. I it got really
difficult. I I had a lot of
disagreements with my leadership and
tried to explain to them, hey, here's my
spreadsheets year-over-year. Here's all
the work we did. Here's the offers we
were seeing coming in. And um I I do
believe they fixed that problem.
Actually, they have ranges like every
you have as you're a large company, you
have to have ranges. You you can't do
any different than that. So, they did
fix that problem after I left.
>> You hired a ton of software engineers at
Netflix and also I'm sure at Meta as
well. How do you identify really strong
software engineers in the hiring
process?
>> So, this is interesting. Um, actually,
I've had success hiring all the way up
until Meta. Metat is a big company like
Google and Amazon and others, Microsoft,
they've because they bring so many
people in and they need to have some
structure and accountability and they
build a system, an interviewing system
where you get to smaller companies and
you're actually now me and three people
on my team plus HR who interviewing
somebody I want to hire, right? And
that's not the way it works. I don't
know about Netflix anymore. That's the
way it was worked when I was there. But,
you know, that's not the way it works at
Meta because they just the company's too
big and they hire too many people and
they need to know that they're giving
fair and consistent standards for
hiring, right? So, um, but I've been
very successful back when when I was
literally making the higher no hire
decisions. Um, and it's curious, I'll
give a couple examples. So, in the late
1990s on that first really good project,
um, we interviewed a woman actually and
um
I was the last one to interview her and
she had been working in like an
automated train software system building
automated train automation software
engine driverless trains
and we our 45minute interview went an
hour and a half and she had two
whiteboards covered with this system and
we're walking through state transitions
and I'm just blown way by like this is
one of the best systems minds I've ever
sat and worked with and her
understanding and ability to explain
these this complex incredibly complex
distributed system not for scale but it
was distributed in terms of the way that
everything fit together the pieces all
interacted well the other people gave
her effectively elite code she was okay
I gave her string version it was okay it
worked but it wasn't they didn't want to
hire her and I told my boss Awesome. And
I said when I hire my boss pushed back,
ironically, you know, my boss was also a
woman, but she was concerned. Well,
these people are kind of lukewarm. I
said, look, this is one of the best
systems engineers I've ever talked to.
She understands complexity. We're
struggling. All these great engineers we
have, we're struggling with the
integration of all these diff disperate
systems we're bringing together. We need
her. And we hired her and she freaking
killed it, right? Absolutely killed it.
And and that's cons that's gone on. Um,
I've I've always felt like when I'm
hiring in small companies for roles for
people on my team, I generally speaking
my my batting average is very close to a
thousand. Um, and and I think it's
because, this is going to be
controversial, I I personally don't love
lead code
because I don't think it really tells
you much about it. It tells you how fast
somebody can write code for a problem
that they probably practiced a hundred
times, right? because people go but but
I will say on the other side of that
when you're hiring at the volume that
these large companies like Meta and
Google do you really don't have any
choice but [snorts] lead code I've you
know does not tell you anything about an
engineer and as I mentioned before
engineering first of all I I don't think
about engineering like software
engineers right I personally believe all
engineering disciplines are all built on
the same foundation and I've mentioned
this earlier uh We were talking that
foundation is the ability to understand
complex systems, a strong technical
intuition and the ability to make
decisions absent good decisions absent
enough data to tell you it's the right
decision. That's an intuition.
And I've seen really really good
engineers move into software and be
phenomenally successful. And I've seen
engineers who nailed the leak code and
these canned system design. and they've,
you know, they practiced all, you know,
you know, um, type ahead, Google type
ahead, whatever the things I give them.
They nail these interviews and they get
in and their engineering work is
terrible and and it's like they're not I
look at their their review packets and
their feedback and I'm like, this person
is not making good engineering
decisions. The quality of their work is
really bad. So I will simply say that if
you have that strong foundational
engineering ability then then you can
learn software and be a phenomenal
software engineer but I don't care how
much you learn about coding if you don't
have a good engineering um foundation
that my it's and you're born with it.
It's like a musician right you can I
like to play guitar but I don't have
that foundational talent that would make
me a phenomenal I'm a good guitar player
I practice a lot but I'll never be
great. So engineering is something the
foundational of engineering. You're born
with it. You have it or you don't. And
and I think a lot of people get
engineering that don't necessarily have
that. And when I recognize that mindset
and realize that I'm talking to a good
engineer, I don't care that their
software is a little subpar because I
feel like I can help them with that. I
can't teach them how to make good
decisions. I I'll give you a really good
example. This is going to blow you away.
So, I was taking some classes, some
graduate level classes at San Jose
State. And in one class I took, my
project partner, I had two partners.
This is kind of funny because this was
just right before I joined Meta. So, you
know, here I am in my 50s and I've got,
you know, people in their 20s, but this
woman joined my team and she was just
finishing her masters in in um civil
engineering, I believe, was working in
wastewater treatment and she decided she
wanted to move to software and this was
her first class because you could go
into the software engineering program at
San Jose State without the undergraduate
requirements and you could catch up on
those requirements over time by taking
basically they said you can start taking
master level but you can't graduate till
you complete these batch these
undergraduate level foundational classes
data structures and you know program.
She was incredibly smart, incredibly
focused and her understanding of like
her the analytical mind, her mastery of
statistics and I just like and I was
telling you know one of my colleagues in
Netflix and I just I want to hire her. I
don't know how to do it, but I want to
hire her. And um and I finally convinced
one of my managers that we should look
at her and maybe we had this idea where
we didn't really have anybody who was
like a date. We didn't have our own
dedicated DE, right, or DS. So, we
thought, well, let's bring her in to
help us with the data analytics. So, we
gave her a video software engineering
problem as a take-home assignment. She
had never really written code. She had
never worked on video. took her three
weeks and she came back and it's like
well she made some rookie mistakes but
damn you know it was like and and so
everybody was like kind of impressed and
it's like well we know she's not a good
software engineer
what do we needed to close a deal and I
suggested let's have her come in and
teach us something which all she knew
was wastewater treatment because she
worked at the Santa Clara County
wastewater facility so she came in and
spent two hours on a whiteboard and I've
realized halfway through this is a
freaking state machine and it's not a
it's a very complex state machine and
and I was just like and we're all just I
mean two hours we're all enthralled
everybody just totally got into it but
we got out and one of the managers who
would have been the hiring manager what
the hell does sewage treatment have to
do with software and I told him I said
look
she's a damn good engineer and when
she's already demonstrated mastery of
like engineering statistics
and I think we can teach her how to
code. And he hired her. He was grumbling
and I ran into him ironically after I
joined Meta. We had an atscale event and
he was there and he David can I talk to
you? He blew me. He said, "She's killing
it." It's like, "How did you know?" I
said, "I can't believe I was so wrong.
How did you know?" And I just told him
straight up,
when you see a brilliant engineering
mind, everything else doesn't matter how
fast they can solve leak code, whatever.
do can they build like a Google type
ahead you know scalable solution or
whatever because these things can all be
learned they can be learned in a very
short time but you can't teach that and
you have that young mind hungry willing
to work hard and and willing to make you
know able to make smart decisions so
that's kind of how I approached hiring
back when I was you know when I was
actually hiring people to bring in to
work for me that doesn't work that
doesn't scale right you can't do that at
Meta you can't do that at Netflix today
or Google maybe Netflix I don't know you
can't do it at at m Google just a legal
and and and you know policy problems you
know everything you'd have to worry
about I just it would break down really
badly but you know so we have to have
the system we have to have so basically
it's like hey we're going to give you a
bar and if you meet this bar you know
higher no higher yes okay level this is
what we can see from what we're you know
and I've had people that they were six
somewhere else and they they said,
"Well, I got an offer of five at Meta."
I was like, "Look,
better to come in under." And I said,
"If you come if you come to Meta as a
five and start immediately executing as
a six, you're going to be blown away by
your bonuses, your multipliers, your RSU
refresh, you're going to be blown away
by the way you get treated by coming in
and really demonstrating that you're
underlevel. But if you get higher at
that higher level and you come in and
you're struggling, you would have been a
really good five, but you're struggling
to execute at that sixth level, it's
just not going to work because there is
no way to fix that. Right? If you get
hired in a company like Met Meta or
Google or I know probably any of the
fang companies and you end up being
overleveled, they don't have a way for
somebody, well, okay, you can leave or
we'll put you to a six because we hired
you as a seven. There's no way to fix
that problem. So when in doubt, go low
and work hard and get that quick
promotion, get those bonus and RSU
multipliers and and you know prove your
metal.
>> You you mentioned in identifying the the
engineering skill set that fundamental
engineering skill set. How do you how do
you identify that like is there a
question you ask or is there certain
things you need to see?
>> I think it's you interview to the
person,
right? Not to the process. So if you
know we have a master's civil engineer
who's expert in wastewater treatment and
it's like it's a hard engineering
problem and if you can demonstrate
mastery of that problem and you can
explain it to engineers that know
nothing and you know to the point where
those of us who got it realize that like
this is just a finite state machine
right I mean after all what is I mean
what is almost engine any engineering I
know when you get into structure and
everything a little different but so
many systems mechanical systems right
you know engines right or whatever they
all end up kind of in some way
connecting back to like states and
transitions and [clears throat] so I
think when you see that again we're
we're we brought this person in is
effectively would be like a new hire a
junior we had a role like as a data
analyst or something um but so we we had
an if we would have brought him in as a
full-on software engineer these
expectations up here, they would have
failed.
So again, that's when you're at a
smaller company, um you you create
flexibility
and you can actually hire and and build
people up.
>> Is there um examples of the strongest
engineers you worked with and you what
made them strong at Netflix? I'm simply
going to say the absolute best engineer,
strongest engineer I've ever worked with
is Jannis Katzanetus. I'm generally
going to try to avoid names, but I I got
to put him out. I met him in 2000 in
video. I [clears throat] brought him in.
He was he left the industry and was
working as a professor in Greece
teaching signal processing. And I
brought him in during the summer break
to to help. I was working on this was in
2010. I was working on some ideas around
parallel encoding. Uh and the the work
we did gave birth to contentbased
encoding which is now how the entire
industry is working. The the we wrote an
early patent on that. He went back to
school but we convinced him to join us
at Netflix a couple years later. He took
that one level further to to um to what
to now the model for encoding for both
Meta and Netflix which is called convex
all encoding which is actually
mathematically delivering the highest
possible quality for a given bandwidth
capability. Um and
he and I work together at innerv video
Netflix and meta. He's an engineers
engineer and one of the most in
brilliant people I've ever known. He
actually developed a model for the co
basically for codec evaluation that's a
costbenefit model. For this amount of
energy you get this amount of codec
efficiency
and and which is revolutionary because
he's very much academic and you you know
and you know you always heard the joke
in theory theory and practice are the
same in practice they're very different.
So his brilliance I think was really
bringing this academic world and forcing
it into the practical world where we can
actually make decisions based on not
what some hypothetical you know you know
two videos you compress can do but
actually you know what happens when we
run this test against 10,000 videos or a
million videos or a billion videos.
>> You've mentioned meta a lot at this
point. Maybe we should go to that. Um
I'm kind of curious what's the story
behind you uh getting recruited to Meta
or working at Meta.
>> Sure. So um as I mentioned earlier the
Netflix culture deck the early one said
that we really should interview often so
we understand our market value right and
I had an outreach from Meta and I don't
remember who it was um [clears throat]
but
it was like 2018
I think 2017 late 2017 I think it was
late 2017
and I told my wife I said yeah you know
Facebook it was fa Facebook at the time
Facebook wants to interview me I said I
want to work there, but I haven't
interviewed in like 12 years. I I think
I need to interview or 10 years,
whatever. So, I went and interviewed
and I I kind of went over I I will say
honestly a bit full of myself because
like you would hear me, we built
Netflix, we built the highest scale in
coding platform in the world, whatever.
And and I got to the interviews and I
was um whiteboarding everything out. I
remember one guy he were good interviews
but this one guy stop said David you
have to understand Facebook cannot solve
their video scale problem with CPUs
and I just I walked away and I emailed
him back later I was like you floored me
right I I never realized and and so I I
I turn eventually I got an offer and I I
turned it down I just wasn't ready at
the time um but I had I had reached out
to this guy and I just told him you know
I thank you for like you know
letting me know that I was very narrow
in how I understood the world of video
because [clears throat] I had no concept
and I want to talk about this about
Facebook's meta scale in a little bit. I
had no understanding or concept. Um
shortly after that Giannis who was in
Netflix pulled me aside and said hey
I've got this offer from Facebook and we
sat and talked about he was talking
about the ASIC. He was talking about all
these things he was going to work on and
I
I saw a passion in him that I hadn't
seen in a little while and and he had
done some really good work at Netflix
but I don't think that the culture again
is not built around individual
contributions. I don't think he ever you
know was getting the joy and I think the
reward and recognition. Remember
recognition is not for an engineer is
not your name in lights.
Sometimes it could be as simple as like
a senior executive saying, "Hey, this is
really good work this person did." And
I'm not [clears throat] saying they
didn't do that at Netflix. I'm just
saying it like
we'll talk about this. Met meta is very
intentional about individual credit. So,
and I think he felt like the problems
weren't big enough for him and he was he
just had this look and I was like, "Wow,
this is amazing." You know, and he's
like, "Aren't you going to try to talk
me out of it?" I was like, "Yes, you're
my friend, right? Is I as an employer,
as your boss, I don't want to lose you,
but as your friend, I'm like, how can
you say no? And I'm not even going to
try because, you know, because I care
about and I I just I wish I could tell
you going there would be the wrong
decision." And [clears throat]
so through that process, I started with
a company. I was only interviewing just
to work on my, you know, interview
muscle. And in the end,
I was just looking across the aisle and
thinking, man, that's freaking hard
problem. And I had a good solid team
doing well. I had a leader lined up
ready to take my place. And just the way
things kind of worked out
[clears throat] in in in 2019. Um, I
ended up leaving Netflix and word got
out and Facebook reached out to me very
quickly. I had to rein because the gap
had been too long, but I got a job offer
and and I took it. I was excited and I
came in um really really excited about
that um role. Um but I but I will have
to say like you know it's really easy if
you have leadership skills and talent
kind of that innate talent to be a
leader it's really easy to grow
organically right the encoding
technology team at Netflix was one
person me and then it was two and then
three four five six then I need a
manager seven 8 10 eventually I had a
director under me and and a handful of
managers and a you know 55 people what
total
and you you know everybody you've grown
into that role you've built trust I came
to a well functioning team I was given
responsibility for 55 60 people at NETA
the video processing team and they
didn't know me from anybody and I feel
like I came in like one of the first
lessons I got and I knew we all knew
that we had problems everybody knew
Facebook video platform there were some
quality problems the scale had been met
the scale challenge had been met which
was a the hardest problem and they were
looking for somebody to help them kind
of let's you know can we be a better
video experience.
I remember early meeting I started
talking about some of the things I saw
that maybe need to be worked on and I
got feedback like David you know
first of all because I told everybody I
really
value and appreciate direct and candid
feedback. Don't ever be afraid to give
me feedback. And I was talking about
something and then and and one of my
people on my team the next week at
oneonone said, "David, do you say you
like candid feedback? Can I be candid?"
I said, "Yeah." He said, "Yeah, you've
been here two weeks. You're already
telling us what we need to do." And then
and and then we were talked about a
little bit. And I said, "So what I think
I hear you saying is I need to shut up
and work on building trust." And that's
what I had never that's a muscle I had
never ever developed before because I
built trust by working with people and
growing over time and just coming in as
a senior leader as a director and you
know and they're asking the company's
asking you we need you to to do change
you know to make help us you know
improve this
is all but you can't just come in at the
same and start and I didn't and also I
will say that, you know, I part of that
was ignorance because I didn't really
fully understand. I knew what some
problems they were having, but I I so I
that kind of I stepped back. I realized,
look, first and foremost, being a leader
is about relationships. Ultimately,
we're an engineering team. We have to
make good engineering decisions. But if
the if the managers reporting to me
don't trust me, we go nowhere and I
fail. And I realize it. So,
[clears throat] that was really good
feedback in the moment um or near the
moment. and and I spent a lot of time
trying to sit listen build trust and and
and I feel I was very successful in that
over the time you know I've been told
even now you know like the team you know
there was a lot of respect there they
knew I respected them even if they were
struggling or needed feedback they knew
I was going to give it to them but but
you know they they knew that I was going
to tell them like it was and I was going
to be honest with them and and so that
was my first lesson like it's really
hard stepping in as a leader of a large
team that's already doing well. If it's
a if it's a broken team, your job is to
unbreak it, right? But if it's a team
that's actually executing well, your job
is to not break it first and then help
it move forward second. And I jumped in
to move forward. So that that was a
really good experience for me. I I
really feel like I mean my saddest thing
about Meta
is that it was a last job
because I feel like if I were to go take
another full-time job at in an
engineering company at a larger
leadership role today, the value the
skills I learned at Meta, I mean, I
would just come in as such a better
organizational and engineering leader,
but I'm just kind of past the point of
really wanting to take on that level of
responsibility. So the only thing I I
wish I could have done, you know, if
there was I wouldn't get wouldn't trade
my Netflix experience, but there was
somehow like maybe I could have had
these two in parallel or something. It
just it the way it worked out or if all
this would have happened but happened 10
years earlier, then maybe I'd be like,
hey, you know, I'm, you know, I'm 55 and
I'm going to leave Meta and I'm going to
go join this other company and really
help them, you know, build this
engineering or but because I learned a
lot. I think I learned the most about
engineering leadership not at Netflix
but at Meta because of the the the the
challenge of the role.
>> Yeah. I'm curious how do you when you
come in as such a senior leader you
mentioned building trust. What does that
mean concretely? Like what do you do if
you're coming in as a senior leader to
build trust with the existing team?
Um, I think first of all taking the time
and I did spend a lot of time in one-on-
ons but you know you you don't want to
get over your skis ahead of your skis.
So really spending you know first of all
this is a very technical role right
video processing even for the director
these decisions are being made you have
to understand at some level why they're
doing what they're doing otherwise you
know
they may not be successful. Um, but I,
you know, it really involved spending a
lot of time in one-on- ones and talking
and asking questions and making notes
and understanding the fundamentals of
the system, the interactions,
understanding the roles, the team, the
people. [clears throat] I mean, one of
the first decisions I had to do was like
because they reorganized when they
brought me in and oh yeah, you need a
manager for this team. I you know it's
an uplevel manager and you can you can
promote or you can hire and you know and
here I am having to make a decision and
I have managers I don't know or I could
hire from externally and I'm just like
and it's like
ultimately I and and some people why
don't you just promote one of your
managers and I'm like well I don't know
him you know I I don't just want to make
a decision because it's politically
correct. So I I sat on that decision. I
got into that trust building mode. I
spent some time talking to them.
Finally, I said, "Okay, now and they
were right. There was already a manager
on the team that would have been the
right manager for the role." But but I
because I told my boss, "Well, if you
thought he was the right one, why didn't
you promote him before you hired me?
Because now you're asking me to own a
decision that I can't that I don't
know." But but I did take the time.
And [clears throat] it was a difficult
relationship at first with that manager
cuz I think, you know, he kind of felt
like this was his role and why isn't he
giving it to me? Is he just going to
hire somebody else? I may have to quit.
But we spent a little time together and
I then I had a one-on-one who said, you
know, I I apologize for the time, but I
just can't make a decision. This is like
huge, right? It's your future, it's my
future, everything. And I don't care
what people tell me. I need to
understand. But I said, but I do believe
at this point I can say with confidence,
you are the right person for this role
and I want to move you into this role.
And that kind of, you know, and then,
you know, by the time he left Meta to do
something new, we had gotten past, you
know, all the trust issues. He
understood who I was. He know, you know,
I don't walk on water. But he knew like
he he no longer assumed the worst. He
always wait a minute, I know I can trust
David. If if I'm understanding this, I
know that's not he would tell me, hey,
you said this. What do you mean? And so
we ended up having a very good trust
relationship, right? And it was really
just all that was about slowing down,
right? not making any rash decisions,
not getting ahead of yourself, not
telling the team what they need to do
and you know just like absorb absorb
absorb and I feel like even like if I
could go back to my 2019 David just
joining Meta
I would even the investment I made was I
don't feel was adequate.
I was like, you that first six months, I
should have just told my boss, I'm in
school and if there's a critical
decision, you and I are going to have to
make it together because I need to
understand
better what my team is doing. I need to
know the people better and and so I
would spend even more time both
technical and people understanding that.
But I I do feel like that early feedback
kind of helped me correct and got me to
a place where I was successful.
I see. [clears throat] Um, at Meta, you
mentioned the scale um, was really
unique. I'm curious, is there any
favorite work or favorite project that
you did at Meta?
>> There's a couple things that I talk I
already talked about the scale bringing
that Netflix quality into the meta
scale, which we were successful. The the
second thing really
we have to talk about is co. So, you
remember my world at Meta. I joined in
late July 2019. By March, nobody was
coming to the office, right? Not even
nine months into my job, we're all
working from home. And to
[clears throat] make matters worse, um,
you know, we the video for I I think it
was all of Facebook, but especially
video. We New Year's Eve was like like
the we started planning for New Year's
Eve in the summer because every New
Year's Eve we would see this huge spike
in traffic for 24 hours. you just like
we know you know and I guess before I
joined perhaps New Year's Eve was a
system breaking but by then everybody
was planning to make sure we were
successful on New Year's Eve. Well by
April 2020 every freaking day was New
Year's Eve in terms of video upload
quantity or volume in terms of streams
lives live every system we had and we're
watching these systems slowly bleeding
out right because we had never run at
that kind of sustained load. we have
some race conditions and all these
things and I'm just like the whole
freaking world you know the prime
minister of India was addressing his
country regularly using Facebook live
streaming
and the whole world is like maintaining
their sanity and continuity and
connection using our apps and so that
was just a huge huge I mean I I was
terrified they the weight you know the
weight of that realizing and I realized
that the connection was a lot more than
video video was like huge and and so but
you know but we all you know from our
homes we all got into and put our heads
down and we we found all these problems
we ironed out the wrinkles in our system
we resolved these race conditions and
got to where we were chugging along at
New Year's Eve every day and the systems
after about a month systems were all
running metrics were holding everything
was really good and so I was really
proud of that and I think
when I joined
Facebook.
I I didn't really understand the value
proposition of the company. Now, I had
Facebook account and I shared pictures
and it's social and yeah, some videos
now and then. I didn't really understand
because I was feeling like it was a very
kind of like I my US- ccentric view of
the company and it's just a social app
that we all share our stuff on. And
I learned in relatively short order,
first of all, I understood what it means
if your customer base is three and a
half billion people. That means that the
the half the world is on your platform.
It means that you know, and again I'm in
no way disrespecting Netflix, phenomenal
company, phenomenal product, but Netflix
has 300 million people. So you could
roughly say that's the top 5%
income in terms of income of the world,
the wealthiest 5%.
Um, Meta has the wealthiest 50%. And the
wealthy is kind of a loaded term because
at the bottom you're talking about
people making $68 a day. And there and
and Instagram and WhatsApp in particular
or Facebook, this is their lifeblood.
you have little mom and pop stores all
through India you know when and you know
I I I'll be in a Uber and the driver it
was actually very early on I was going
to a business meeting in in um Seattle
and the Uber driver you know where do
you work I said Facebook he oh my gosh I
love Facebook you know he's from Somalia
he's in my family we're all across the
world and if it weren't for WhatsApp we
could not even we we would totally lose
touch but WhatsApp keeps us connected
I'm just like so it was this realization
that unfolded over time of what a
phenomenal product and and product this
was but not face just Facebook company
but how important our work was because
again when people talk about social in
the US that you know I don't care if it
was Tik Tok or or Facebook or Instagram
they always kind of talk about the good
and bad side of this that you know fake
news whatever bad whatever but we are
totally oblivious to how we are
improving the lives of people in the
rest of the world. And when I learned
that I just I realized it's like you
I've always
loved doing what I do but I've you know
all of a sudden the work I do is making
a difference. I realize nobody's going
to in India is going to say wow David
Rona really changed my life but in a
small piece right that you know they
will say that the company Meta changed
their life gave them a business where
they could support their family gave
them a platform where they could share
social videos and make money you know
and improve their standard of living you
know gave them a way to stay in touch
with their family distribute around the
world they will say the company made a
difference in their lives and I really
liked being a part of that I I I really
at the end of the day that and I tried
try to explain this to people who don't
work for the company or they're griping
about this or that or you know whatever
you just don't understand right how good
it feels to know like you're making in a
small small way you're actually making a
difference in the world
>> coming to the end of the interview I
wanted to do some reflections on your
career um I think first question I'm
kind of curious about is when it comes
to work life balance throughout your
career how did that change throughout
the different roles you had
>> I had the first
really visionary executive that I was
working for in the late 90s. You know,
she gave us she sold us on something we
were passionate about and we all worked
our um and I was working hard not
because
the expectation was there. It was
because we were trying to catch up and
we did. Um but when I went to the
startup the expectation was when I was
at inner video it was a 24/7 expectation
and I was going to work usually at 10
10:30 in the morning coming home usually
an early night would be 10 at night a
late night would be like sometimes 2 or
3 in the morning and you oftent times
seven days a week and um you know we
trying to get to the IPO and then we got
the IPO but we got to get these wh these
new wins wins, bundling winds to get
revenue so that our stock price will be
up or whatever. Um, in January of 24 or
2004,
[clears throat] I started feeling ill on
a Sunday
and was not getting better through the
week. On that Friday, I went to an
emergency room. I was having a serious
serious problem. My wife took me to the
emergency room where I was immediately
diagnosed even before they had proven
it. The doctor told me this is colon
cancer and I was like my digestive
system was blocked and it creates a very
catastrophic quick death situation. So I
just I basically just fell off from a
health perspective in one week. I had
been driving myself,
driving, push, push, push, and boom, I
just fell off a cliff. And I woke up,
you know, I was in the hospital a
Saturday.
Um, and I was on machines and they had
gotten me stable, and they were going to
take, it took a week to get me
physically strong enough to have a
surgery to remove the cancer. Um, and
I'm laying in there in the hospital, and
I know this kind of sounds cliche, but I
was a dad. I had a 2-year-old, a
four-year-old, and a seven-year-old.
And when you work those kind of hours,
you know, my my my my older my daughter
knew me reasonably well. We had had some
time and some relationship. My oldest
son we had, but my youngest didn't even
know who I was. I mean, he knew who I
was, but I was just the guy who come in,
you know, and
you're sitting there literally thinking
you're at the end of your life because I
was I was stage three. It had lymph node
metastasis.
When I finally got out, I had two
surgeries, chemotherapy, but when I got
out of the hospital 3 weeks later, I was
in for three weeks and multiple
surgeries and everything to recover. Um,
my five-year survival prognosis was
about 25%.
And so, while I was in the hospital
reflecting, I realized that like like
this is wrong, right? And I, you know,
this was only four years into her video.
And so, when I came out, it was like I
can't do this anymore. And I told my
boss in her video, look, I you know, I
still want to work here, but I can't do
this. And even and I realized it not
just cuz I was sick. This is you simply
if you're working at a company where
they put those demands on you and those
expectations that if you're not there
late, you're going to get fired. The
best thing you can do is leave,
right? And and they were actually using
work hours to compensate for really bad
leadership. So, I actually did some of
my best engineering at innerv video
after I got out of the hospital because
I had to get back ramp back up to
full-time. But I had work life balance
thrust upon me. And from that point
forward, it became something that I was
passionate about that I was never going
to be a leader that put expectations on
people that you kill yourself for the
job, you know, and literally that's what
we were doing. Even though most people
don't die, they're they're they're
they're they're
selling their life, they're trading
their life, their experiences, their
children, whatever, anything else they
could have for a job. And there's no job
that's worth that. And that's where I
appreciate when I got to Netflix. You
know, that was a shock for me for them
to tell me in the interview that we
don't value 27 work, 247 work. And and
if you come in and work that way, we're
probably that doesn't mean you're going
to be successful. But if you come in and
make really good decisions in the time
you're here and go work, enjoy your
weekends and your time away,
we're gonna love you. And I'm just like,
wow. And I realize that. So that's now
part of my DNA. And I think that what I
would like to say is for everybody else
that happen to be watching this, don't
wait till you get cancer or have a heart
attack to wait for you to realize work
life balance is is is, you know,
critical.
Bake it into your DNA at an early age.
Learn how to take time off. Take
vacation. leave your company alone for a
week, whether it's going to kill them or
not. If they can't survive without you
for seven days, that's not your problem,
that's their problem. And the only way
you can make them understand that
problem is for you to leave and make
them face that problem and fix it. And
so and and and then I I
and I understand like cuz you know,
having worked at Meta, at Netflix, these
are performanceoriented companies.
And a lot of people I think feel like
well you know you have to work if you
don't work hard if you don't work all
the time. But I think what we're doing
is we're misunderstanding
right remember there there's a poster at
Meta that I just love. It's a rocking
horse. There's a picture of a like a
silhouetted rocking horse and it says
don't mistake motion for progress.
Right? And I think that that that
we in order to have work life balance,
we need to understand about our role and
we need to work you work with your boss
on this. What are the most important
things I need to do? What are the
biggest impacts I can deliver to Netflix
or Meta or Google? What are the things
that really really matter? And the other
stuff, just let your boss know, I'm not
going to do this. And if it matters to
you, I don't have time to do it. And if
it matters, we have to get somebody else
or you have to help me adjust my
priorities so that I can get it done.
The worst thing you can do is simply
like if your boss is not giving you
reasonable goals and not planning,
giving you clear context around what's
expected for a review cycle, the worst
thing you can do is just try to to me,
you know, do everything there because
you end up doing work that maybe wasn't
that important anyway. And so we do have
to own our own, you know, to a certain
extent. I realize this is for somebody
who just got out of college, so maybe a
little hard to to think of, but you
really do have to learn how to own your
time and manage your time and make
decisions because you can't do
everything. It as a in out of work, you
may want to, you know, do marathons
every week and do all this other stuff
and whatever. You can't do everything.
You have to start picking the things
that really matter. It's the same way in
work. And I do believe, you know, as
engineers, you know, anybody's working
in a in a environment like Google or a
fang company, there are going to be
times where we have to put our head down
and crunch. It may mean working
weekends. It may mean working late in
the evenings. Um, but that has to be the
exception, not the not the rule. It has
to be the exception. You you know,
you're getting up to you've been working
on something all all. You've been got
your head down. Now you got, you know,
you're getting to the end. You're about
to roll this feature out. you may have
to spend a little extra time getting it
out. It's like, okay, so I'll plan for
it. Like I know that, hey, in, you know,
like in like e like sometime May, June,
I'm going to have to get my head down. I
may have to work a lot to get this
across the finish line, but then I'm
going to pull back out and then I'll
take a vacation or what, you know, you
have to have that mindset. And again,
you always have to make sure your
manager is giving you clear context on
what really matters and focus on those
things. And I think you find work life
balance happens even at a challenging
high performance company like Netflix or
Meta.
>> When you look back on all the companies
that you worked on, I'm curious which
one do you think you learned the most at
or which one you know taught you the
most and why?
>> My last four jobs each did their piece.
The first job of first of the four
turned me into a full-fledged high
performance software engineer. I mean
performance by the problems you solve
not by the hours you work. The second
job gave me a really good video
foundation. Netflix you know was a zero
to one right people who were at Facebook
from 2008 2012 understand if they're
still here understand how you know that
early company where you're building a
zero to one product versus you know
working at a mature company.
>> [clears throat]
>> So I I you know I think I learned a lot
about leadership about hiring firing
um and and and context setting context
and executing and crossunctional these
things I all learned at Netflix and
brought to Meta. What I came to meta
lacking was an understanding of
objective
like planning
reviews and performance and having an
objective process. And I I I
mean PSC time was both like the most
dreaded time of the year for me and my
favorite time of the year, right? is one
of the things I really and I I I mean
this because you know
Meta
is overindexed on individual credit
and the whole like you know you're
everybody writes their self reviews and
their manager turns it into a a review a
performance packet.
It [clears throat] brings in feedback
and you know lines up things with goals
and
and then that's brought into a large
group and of what we call calibrations
where you're you know people will
challenge right it's because every
manager thinks their team is the best
team on the planet and their engineers
are the best engineers on the planet and
the the reality is where other managers
you're convincing other managers not
through arguments or you know the
pushing hard but through data convincing
them that this engineer deserves this
level and and that they were the ones to
get credit and we would argue a lot wait
this project who worked on this project
who did what who gets the credit and
like that's it's something we take so
seriously and and to me it was so
important is is like taking the time and
having the conversations a across a
larger team of leaders
and understanding how individual
engineers, how they impacted, how their
impact landed, how they moved the
needle, um how they, you know, how they
brought other engineers through, how
they led projects. Um, and making and
getting that credit down on paper. When
when you leave Meta, the one thing that
you get to bring with you is every
single performance review package you
was ever written. Everything I did at
Meta, every negative feedback you need
to get better, every great win is all
cast in stone. Not only do I have that,
2,000 years from now when they're
unearthing like and they find meta hard
drives, they find my stuff. They're
going to know what I did at Meta, right?
That's how important Meta takes
individual achievement. And I think that
that I to me it's one of the best things
about the company. There there's a lot
of great things about Meta, but I feel
like I had always heard horror stories
about oh the PSC performance curves,
everything else. And then I got into
meta. I was like, you know, this really
matters. And so at the end of the day,
being able to the greatest joy I ever
had was having one of my direct reports
and handing them a redefineses
expectations
rating.
There's nothing as a leader and it
doesn't matter that my rating was mess.
I had like two rees on my team over like
over the course of a year. I this is
like and and I have GES and but even the
ones that were not doing well and I had
to give them like hey you know they're
below expectation you know trying to
work with them to get back up that that
all is so important. It gets back to the
people thing right and so I really
valued that work. That's what I learned
at Meta more than I I mean I learned a
lot. I learned I used to think scale was
sc you know I read books and took
classes and you know xyz you know
sharding partitioning and microservices
and I get the meta and all those books
these guys don't know what they're good
books they really didn't know what they
were talking about nobody understands
scale at that level except for a few
companies that are dealing with like you
know billions of users and all the so
anyway these are the two big things I
learned and I to me the most valuable
one and the one that I think that I got
from Meta that I would bring to the next
job if I was to take a full-time job was
how to establish a system for objective
planning, review, and performance.
>> Is there a top book that had an impact
on your career? And if so, what is it?
>> Yeah. So, I'm really going to date
myself here, but the book that I
immediately came to mind when I saw this
question was 12 Secrets to Microsoft
Success.
>> [clears throat]
>> This book came out in the late 90s and
um there were some real there was really
some radical thinking. I mean you know I
mean we look at Microsoft as a very
different company than it was in the
90s. In the '90s everybody thought
Microsoft was going to own the world and
everybody's you know Windows everywhere.
But [clears throat] there was there was
some really radical thinking at that
company, right? Um in their baked into
their culture, right? The the concept of
betting the company, right? And I saw
that at Netflix, right? Amazon, Meta,
right? You see, and not nec it's not
like you're doing a casino bet all in,
but you see a big opportunity, you're
literally betting the company on it. um
the the whole thing of like you know
let's quit saying failure is bad right
there is such a thing as good failure
right and you expect it and if a
company's executing well and healthy
things are going to fail projects are
going to fail people are going to fail
engineers are going to be working on
something it's not going to work out the
way they want it and and the takeaway
from that right we're you can fail on a
big engineering investment in meta it's
not that you fail it's how you fail what
you learned and what you bring forward
so that people can see that Yeah, this
this was a rational bet was a reasonable
bet and they did it and it didn't work
and and they've they've really handled
it well. They managed a risk. They got
out early. So, you can failure can be
success, right? If you based on how you
manage it. Um Microsoft was the first
company to publicly state a a policy of
hiring the top 5%. Their target was to
hire the top 5% of all software
engineers in the world or you know and
they set up their interview and
screening which is kind of a predecessor
to what we do now at the fang companies.
Um and I think that that you know that
was really revolutionary dog fooding
right the term dog fooding was invented
by Microsoft
they talk about that in the book right
before people would work on projects
that products they never saw they never
ran they never tested they didn't
experience bugs you know when Micros
when Bill Gates forced everybody on the
NT team to the whole company is going to
shift to NT server when NT server was
failing badly put all the bugs in this
OS in the in the like 9596 in front of
the entire company and All of a sudden,
this this operating system that couldn't
ship started getting fixed, moving,
moving, moving. Um, and then the crazy
thing that they talked about in that
book was somewhere between Windows 95
and and when the book was written, when
Microsoft was growing leaps over bounds,
Bill Gates instituted a companywide
hiring freeze. And and it's like, what?
You know, shocks you. Well, he felt they
were hiring too many people too fast and
they were investing too much money in
things that didn't matter. And if you
you is you're too old for this probably,
but um in Carta Bob, if you remember
Microsoft Bob, these silly little
animated icons, all these silly things
that Microsoft was doing that were
pointless. And as soon as he instituted
a hiring freeze, he forced his
executives to start killing projects and
putting the people on stuff that
mattered because he felt like hiring was
getting out of control. Like we're
hiring too many people. We're just
putting them everywhere. People are
working on things that don't matter.
We're losing control of the company. And
he instituted a hiring freeze that
basically they ended up cutting like the
bottom 20% which they should have done
anyway. You know, a healthy business is
and we're actually much better at that
now. like you know Meta's pretty
aggressive at cutting you know projects
that aren't proving out that didn't
happen back then right the companies
like once you got this established team
and people and your little thing things
just didn't get cut so that was pretty
radical so I think you know Microsoft
introduced some engineering leadership
concepts that really I don't believe
existed before Microsoft and you know
Amazon Google Um, as much as we all
tried, Netflix, mad as much as we all
tried in the early days to not be evil
like Microsoft, we ended up taking a lot
of their, that was Google's motto, by
the way, don't be evil because Microsoft
was considered the evil empire, the dark
side, you know, whatever. Um,
but we all took they actually were the
ones that kind of established some of
the early like model for modern
engineering. you know, Microsoft brought
us some of these engineering, Amazon
brought us the concept of, you know,
rather than having very expensive,
highly reliable hardware. Let's have
really cheap
hardware and design around failures, you
know, and so these things we all kind
Google brought, we all picked that up
and it all kind of worked together. But
I feel like Microsoft was the first one
and that book I read just stuck with me
all this time. Even when I see like
before 2022 and the big crash, I was
just looking I was like, we can't keep
hiring people at this rate. It doesn't
the math doesn't work, right? It wasn't
just us. It was everybody because during
co we were all like, yeah, we're growing
higher, higher, higher and everybody
accelerated their hiring, but it's like
nobody decelerated and and it's like
boom, right? All of a sudden we had that
contraction and boom. So everybody had
to reset. So I think that had all the
fang leaders read the 12 secrets to
Microsoft success, they would have
recognized in like late 21 that the
hiring was out of control and maybe we
need to slow it down.
>> When you look back on your career, is
there anything you regret that maybe
other people could learn from?
>> Um,
a few regrets. I think
my early years I think my first six
years out of school which is actually a
long time was wasted at very large
failing companies.
The even if the like General Motors spun
off Hughes but Hughes failed, IBM sold
off the division I was in to Seammens
but that division failed. I mean I think
that that that
the only regret I think would be like
you know making I was making a good
salary. Okay, I got an easy job,
whatever. Not really thinking about like
I was only thinking in the moment and I
I really feel like I kind of wasted that
time. I wasn't really thinking about
growth. And I do think we need to think
about growth. We don't need to stress
about it. We don't need to be like
ambitious like I'm going to be a vice
president in like 10 years or whatever.
But we as software engineers especially,
I'm only talking about software
engineering now, not leadership.
Everything [clears throat] we do is
going to be obsolete five years from
now. Right? When I joined meta the boot
camp the whole the the whole system for
the the dev environment everything is
completely replaced. I went through boot
camp as a director was pretty proficient
and when I go to IC it's like oh what is
this everything's changed you know so
everything's going to be obsolete
they're new technologies and the only
way and this is what I believe I have
been successful at you know is
always pushing forward and trying to
stay to the edge and always learning
more learning new things new engineering
skills and the last thing I want to ask
is if you could give yourself advice at
the beginning of your career knowing
what you know now what would you say
>> try to work on hard problems right if
you're work if your job is as an
engineer if your job is not difficult
you're not growing so
you know maybe if you've been working on
something and it was really hard now
it's kind of flatlined enjoy a little
bit of rest think about it and then you
know and I'll be speaking like if you're
a meta for example where it's very easy
to move if you've gotten to where you're
feeling your current role is not very
challenging there's so much going on at
the company go find something else. Get
back into a hard problem, right? And and
and push yourself forward because it's
the hard work, the hard problems that
move us forward, right? And and help us
grow.
Um and then I think, you know,
to a young engineer joining companies,
the size of the company is irrelevant.
Sometimes everybody should work for a
small company at some point in their
life. I believe um startups, everybody
should try a startup, right? Especially,
it's easier when you're younger than
when you're when you're older. But
be careful not to get too enamored by
the technology.
If you join a small company, a startup,
or even a big company like like you
know, Meta, I mean,
Mark is an incredibly visionary leader,
right? And you know, he's navigating
this world and and trying to make
decisions and keep the company focused,
right? So, and Reed Hastings was an
incredibly visionary leader, right? But
Reed Hastings was a visionary leader in
1999 when Netflix had four people. So,
really what you want to do is make sure
you're working for visionary leaders and
not just visionary, they need to be able
to execute as well. So, vision is good,
but if you can't execute against that
vision, you go nowhere. So, um, any
company you're working at, make sure
your leadership is really looking
forward, thinking forward, and again to
Reed Hastings's point, you know, making
you dream of of sailing the seas and not
just, you know, cutting lumber for a
ship.
Um, again, work life balance.
you're out of school, you just start
your new job. You need to plan, be
intentional about not working, about
taking time off, about making sure
you're you're you have a life. Work life
balance, right? It's work, it's life.
They're intention. We have to work to
have a life, but we have to live in
order to work. And so, you want to try
to keep the balance is trying to keep
those two where one doesn't dominate the
other. And and and actually find as an
engineer because we love working on
problems. When you get to that place,
you're actually doing really good work.
you love what you're doing, but you're
also enjoying time off. You know, you're
enjoying your family or whatever it is
you like to do in your time off. And the
last thing I will say which is complete
this is for anybody
when you get out of college when you're
early in your career this is the last
thing I would have talked to myself
about is your financial planning should
start on day one because what's going to
happen not just an engineer but anybody
who's successful as a as a you know as a
technical leader a contributor a leader
is over time you're going to make more
money. And if you don't have a
thoughtful plan about about how you're
going to allocate your spending, living
expenses, car, recreation, short-term
savings, long-term savings, then as you
make more money, it's just you're not
going to know where it's going and
you're going to miss the biggest
opportunity you have, and that's that to
bake into your DNA this whole model of
spending, saving, spending, and
thoughtful financial management. And if
you're thoughtful in your 20s with just
small regular contributions to long-term
savings and managing your budget and not
getting over your skis in terms of of
extended credit or debt, by the time
you're in your early 40s, you won't
necessarily be able to retire unless you
got lucky, like joined a Facebook or
Netflix early on, but you'll be
financially independent to the point
where you don't money is not an issue
anymore and you could take a lesser
paying job. You wouldn't have to worry
about what about the mortgage, what
about you the college or what about this
or that. But it all starts from your
first day on a job. So, the last thing I
will say is is is be really really smart
and thoughtful about your finances from
day one and make sure you're ready like
when you're getting into your late 40s
and early 50s that you're actually
feeling pretty good about your financial
future. Like, hey, I could retire or if
I lost my job, we'd be okay, right? I
could go do something else at half my
salary and we'd be okay because we we've
set ourselves up for that. But if you
get into your 50s and you haven't
planned, it's not your 401k alone is not
going to do it right. If you have and
social security is certainly not going
to do if you haven't planned, then you
get in this situation. It's an
unfortunate situation where a lot of
people I know have found themselves
where you're kind of stuck and you're
having trouble getting new jobs. You
can't work at the with the energy level
you used to have and and you're not
sure. You know, you know, my joke was
always that if I didn't get retirement
right, I'd be a greeter at Walmart, you
know, but it's not really a joke, right?
But but
you know, you'd be surprised how many
engineers have been working and making a
good living, you know, and they're now
in their 50s and they have not had any
rational plan for retirement and they're
in no position to retire. And there's
really as an engineer, there's no reason
for that. If you if you're a good
engineer and you're gainfully employed
for 30, 35 years, there's no reason why
you should not retire very comfortably.
>> All right. Well, thank you so much for
your time today, David. I really
appreciate you sharing your career
story.
>> Uh, it's been a great conversation,
Ryan. Thanks for having interest and
feeling like I have something valuable
to share. So, um, thanks a lot.
>> Absolutely. And is there anything you
want to direct people's attention to?
Uh, at the now at the end of the
conversation,
>> you can find me on LinkedIn and I'm
happy to have a especially for for
younger people. I'm not a financial
planner and I'm not going to plan your
finances, but I have about 10 slides I
put together to give you a starter. And
if somebody wanted to talk about
finances, I would give them a few my
thoughts on how you could start making
smart financial decisions as a as a new
graduate, you know, young and even if
you're in your 40s and start early 50s
and starting to stress out about your
prospects for retirement, I could talk
to you about that. If you're working,
you know, if you're a people leader and
you want to talk about um performance,
planning, reviews, hiring, firing, happy
to have those conversations. Um if
you're an engineer, um happy to have
those conversations with you talking
about your career growth.
>> Awesome. Okay. Well, I will put your
LinkedIn in the show notes so people
have that. So, again, thank you for your
time, David.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to